Timing and Subtitles by The Immortal Team @mkdoramas
동기화 및 자막 by The Immortal Team @mkdoramas
Goblin
♬  See ya never gone my way  ♬
All the moments with you... are blindingly bright.
너와 함께한 시간 모두 눈부셨다.
Because the day was good,
날이 좋아서
because the day was not good,
날이 좋지 않아서
because the day was good enough.
날이 적당해서
♬   Through the endless daydream   ♬
♬  Through the endless daydream  ♬
Every day was good.
모든 날이 좋았다.
[Goblin – Special Summons Part 1 – Back to the Living] ♫  There I walk with you in  ♫
♫  There I walk with you in  ♫
Now, the special..
자, 한 번 스페셜
Let's do it specially.
-네 -스페셜하게 해봅시다.
Don't you feel like Eun Tak's going to come?
은탁이가 올 것 같지 않아요?
- Because it's a radio booth? - Yes.
- 아, 라디오라서? - 네.
That's nonsense.
무슨 말도 안 되는..
Cue.
큐.
Hello. I am Yoo In Na for the Goblin Summon Special.
안녕하세요 도깨비 소환 스페셜로 찾아 온 유인나,
I am Lee Dong Wook. Nice to meet you.
이동욱입니다. 반갑습니다.
Not long ago, Goblin, which was loved by a lot of viewers, has ended.
얼마 전 시청자 여러분들의 많은 사랑을 받으며 막을 내린 도깨비!
But then, there are still a lot of people who have yet to get over it.
그런데 아직도 이 '깨비후유증'을 앓고 계신 분들이 굉장히  많다고 해요.
That's right. I am also one of those.
맞습니다, 저도 그 깨비후유증을 앓고 있는 사람중에 한 명이고
- Well... Miss In Na, you are also one of them. - Yes.
- 뭐, 인나씨도 물론이잖아요? - 네.
Honestly, we had a group chat
사실 저희 단체채팅하는 방이 있는데,
and after the drama ended we all felt empty.
드라마 끝난 다음 날 허하다고,
- That's what everyone said. - Everyone was sad.
- 그랬었죠. - 다 모두가 좀 슬펐죠?
That's right. But seeing your face again today...
맞습니다, 근데 오늘 또 이렇게 인나씨 얼굴 보니까
- It's nice, right? - It is.
- 반갑죠? - 좋네요.
Yes. It's nice to see you.
- 네. - 네, 반갑습니다.
So we have prepared something.
그래서 저희가 한 번 준비를 해봤습니다.
We will hear stories and wishes about the one that you have waited for every week.
매주 깨요일을 기다리시던 시청자분들의 소원과 사연을 받아서
Goblin Special, we'll bring out the Goblin.
스페셜하게 도깨비를 소환해보는 도깨비 소환 스페셜!
We are the same age.
동갑이거든요?
We have perfect chemistry.
찰떡 호흡.
Am I not cute?
제가 안귀엽나요?
[Grim Reaper
때려?
[Goblin
하나, 둘
I'm saying they're all pretty in my eyes./i>
아니 일단 내 눈엔 다 이쁘다니까?
Right before our last filming... [Deok Hwa's self camera]
마지막 촬영을 앞두고
You didn't forget what you promised for the rating, right?i>
공약거신거 안 까먹으셨죠?
[Delivering Secretary Kim's promise for the high ratings!!]
I'm like TT
[Goblin's behind the scenes will be revealed]
보시죠.
So we will introduce the first story.
네, 그럼 첫번째 사연을 소개해 드리겠습니다.
I'm looking forward to it.
- 아, 기대됩니다. 예, 또 간만에. - 네, 기대해주세요.
Our honey DJ's voice.
우리 꿀D의 목소리를.
This comes from someone whose ID is "Wanna go to Maple country to eat beef."
네, 아이디가요 '단풍국에 소 먹으러 갈래' 님이에요.
Goblin already ended... now what do I live for?
도깨비가 벌써 끝나다니, 이제 무슨 낙으로 사나요?
The drama Goblin who came with a thud.
첫사랑처럼 쿵쿵하고 다가온 드라마, 도깨비.
Would their first meeting be like that, too?
그들의 첫 만남도 그랬을까요?
Reading the story... it must be about the first drama meeting, first script reading, first shoot...
사연을 보니까 드라마 첫 미팅, 첫 리딩, 그 다음에 첫 촬영, 뭐
A lot of moments come to mind.
정말 많은 순간들이 떠오릅니다.
Goblin who is filled with heart fluttering and good memories.
설레고 좋았던 기억들로 가득한 도깨비.
Should we summon the first meeting?
첫 만남의 순간들 저희가 한 번 소환해볼까요?
- Yes. - Let's take a look together.
- 네. - 네, 함께 보시죠.
[Press conference 2016 November 21]
♫ 널 정말 사랑해 ♫
[Ji Eun Tak
♫ 사랑해 사랑하는데 ♫
[Grim Reaper
♫  왜 변했다고 하는건데 왜 ♫
[And another couple]
♫  왜 화내고  ♫
[Goblin
♫  삐지고  ♫
Now here's the best couple.
지상 최고의 커플입니다 여러분!
[Dignity of the Best Couple]
블랙앤 화이트네요.
♬ You're the most beautiful ♬
♫ 이뻐 ♫
- The outfits... - Did you match your outfits?
- 이 날 공교롭게 의상이 또.. - 의상을 맞춘 건가요?
No. But black and white...
아닌데, 블랙앤 화이트로 또.
I was so surprised when I came to the venue.
저도 현장와서 보고 깜짝 놀랐어요.
Our drama, Goblin is a strange, beautiful, lonely and great story.
저희 드라마 도깨비는 이상하고 아름답고 쓸쓸하고 찬란한 이야기입니다.
It is a fantasy drama.
그런 판타지 드라마를 하고 싶었구요.
I was able to work with
그래서 이렇게 멋진 배우들과 같이
all these amazing actors.
작업을 하게 됐어요.
All the people knew that by Gong Yoo...
아시는 분들은 다 아실거에요, 제가 공유 씨에게
By Gong Yoo...
공유 씨에게 한
I was rejected for 5 years from trying to cast him.
5년을 걸쳐서 까였어요.
I was wondering if I had to wait a long time again this time, but...
이게 '오래 기다려야 되지 않을까 이번에도' 했는데, 금방 답을 주셨어요.
He said he would do it if I was okay with a shy and fearful Goblin.
'이렇게 소심하고 겁 많은 도깨비라도 괜찮으시다면 이 작품을 하겠습니다' 라고
[Pretty cool?!]
답변을 주셔가지고.
I have a bit of fear towards dramas.
제가 드라마를 조금 두려워했던 게 있어요.
Honestly, the words that really had a great impression on me were...
사실 제가 들은 말 중에 가장 인상 깊었던 말은,
Just because my previous project was a huge success, I won't be cocky.
'전 작품이 잘됐다고 뭐, 건방 떨지 않고
She said, I will really, really work hard. Trust me.
정말 최선을, 진짜 진짜 열심히 할거야 날 믿어줘' 라는 말씀에
When I saw that she spoke to me so candidly...
허심탄회하게 다 얘기하시는 걸 보고
I was also moved.
저도 감동을 받았던 것 같아요.
So I thought I should follow the writer's lead.
저 작가님을 믿고 따라가야겠다는 생각을 그때 했던 것 같아요.
I really wanted the role and told her I really wanted to do it.
저승사자 역할이 굉장히 탐났구요, 제가 먼저 하고싶다고 말씀을 드렸고
Especially since Gong Yoo hyung was the Goblin so it was nice.
특히 도깨비가 공유 형이라서 굉장히 좋았고요
With the thought of working with Hyung I thought of having fun without burden. That's how we are filming right now.
형이랑 같이 한다면, 저도 또 부담없이 한 번 재밌게 놀아볼 수 있겠다라는 생각으로 굉장히 즐겁게 촬영하고 있습니다.
[Lee Dong Wook] [Yook Sung Jae]
긴장하지마.
To be able to work with 10 million viewers actor Gong Yoo... [10 million actor Gong Yoo]
'부산행'을 찍은 천만배우 공유...
Seems like his mom told him to do that, right?
엄마가 시킨 것 같죠?
I am very nervous.
정말 떨리네요.
Why is it so burdening from the start?
왜 부담 줘 시작부터..
That's why I am asking you. How did you get through that door?  What are you?
그러니까 묻잖아, 너 저 문 어떻게 통과한거야, 너  대체 뭐야?
No matter how I think about it, I think you are really the Goblin.
난 암만 생각해도 아저씨가 도깨비 맞는거 같거든요.
I love you.
사랑해요~
[The actors that bring their characters to life]
반가워요, 써니에요.
Uncles, you are all too naive and careless.
삼촌들 너무 부주의하고 천진난만해.
Grim Reaper who might be a murderer in his past life.
전생에 살인자 였을지도 모르는 저승사자..
As if you didn't kill a single ant in your past life!
지는 아주 전생에 길 가는 개미 한 마리 안 죽였을!!
As you hit and hit her you let go and then you hit her again.
놓고 팡팡 때리면서 놓치고 그 다음에 때리는 것 까지
When you hit me, you can hit me comfortably.
진짜 때리시기 편한대로, 머리라서.
Cue.
하이, 큐!
[Eun Tak lost her parents when she was young]
♫ 신데렐라는 어려서 부모님을 잃고요 ♫
Let's go one more time.
다시 한 번 갈게요.
♫ By her stepmother ♫
♫ 계모와 ♫
[She was abused by her aunt and cousins.]
♫ 언니들에게 놀림을 받았더래요 ♫
Cut!
컷!
You can hit my head.
머리 때리셔도 돼요.
Cue!
큐!
Cut!
컷.
I'm okay.
저는 아무렇지 않아요.
Do you repay me like this for raising you?
네가 키워준 은혜를 이따구로 갚어?
Like this? Like this?
이따구로, 이따구로, 이따구로?
Give it to me. It's mine, so give it to me.
주세요, 제꺼니까 주세요.
Starting from the first day you are really suffering a lot.
첫날부터 엄청 고생하시네요.
This doesn't even count as suffering.
이거는 고생하는 축에도 안 끼죠.
Gong Yoo really suffered a lot.
와, 진짜 공유 형은 진짜 몸 고생 많이 했어요.
I really didn't have any time to practice.
연습할 시간이 너무 없었어요.
We had to cram everything, so...
벼락치기 해서 온거라
it was harder than I thought.
생각보다 더 어려웠던 것 같아요.
My body is so...
검이 너무
The sword was huge and heavy.
크고 무겁고 이래서.
[The sword that is bigger and heavier than you see]
안 그래도
I didn't do a good job and didn't look right to begin with. And the sword made it much more difficult and hard to handle.
잘 못하고 초보한테 더 힘들고 버벅댔던것 같아요.
Lift it quickly.
이렇게 빨리 들어서
You have to continue to turn.
내가 계속 이러면서 이렇게 가야 돼.
If you don't do it all at once
한 번 할때 모든 걸 쏟아붓지 않으면
it would cause an NG. So you have to pour it all at once for the action scenes.
NG가 나기 때문에, 정말 모든 힘을 다 쏟아 부어서 하거든요? 저 액션 같은건 특히.
It was a drama that had a lot of difficult scenes.
- 유난히 힘든 씬들이 많은 드라마였어서. - 맞아요, 네.
Cut! It's an okay!
컷! OK입니다!
I am good with using my bare hands.
맨손으로 하는건 잘하는데.
[You are cool whatever you do]
무엇을 해도 멋진 당신
Now that I have tried sword action, I think doing it with bare hands is easier.
검 액션을 해보니까 맨손으로 하는게 더 쉬운거 같아요.
I'm not sure if it's because I am used to it.
제가 그게 익숙해서 그런진 몰라도.
[Should I show you?]
한번 보여줘?!
The camera might break so...
카메라 깨질까봐 제가..
We'll take a look at that once more.
자 우리 조금 더 서둘러 볼게요!
Nice to meet you.
반가워요.
[Everyone suffered individually, compared to the Goblin]
각자 따로 고생했던 도깨비 내외와 달리
I'm Sunny.
써니에요.
[With a harmonious atmosphere, the start of the first filming of Sunny
화기애애한 분위기에서 첫 촬영을 시작한 써니♡저승사자
Seon Hyo?
선희요?
Nice to meet you.
반가워요.
[Should I do it like this?]
머리 넘길 때 이렇게 할까?
Ohh!
어어어.
Yeah!
어어어~
Who will pay for it?
돈은 누가 낼꺼야?
[Her. Sunny.]
쟤요. 써니.
Like the guys who do hip hop... like this...
힙합하는 애들처럼 막
[This time with a gun bang!]
그게 좋으면
Why? You should do this at the end.
왜 마지막에 이거해.
[Sunny who burst out laughing with Reaper's sense of humor]
저승이의 유머에 빵 터진 써니
It's fun.
아니야, 재밌어서 재밌어서.
[Peachy Couple who are so sweet from their first taping]
첫 촬영부터 깨 쏟아지는 피치 커플
Then you should act like you're dying.
죽는시늉 같은거 해줘야죠 그럼.
- It was the 7th episode when I first met you. - Yes.
-인나씨랑 처음만난게 또 저 육교였고 -네.
So, that overpass became a place of affection for me.
그래서 저 육교가 굉장히 좀 애착이 가는 장소?가 됐어요.
That's right. Should we visit that place sometime?
맞아요, 가끔 놀러갈까요 우리? 거기?
Let's leave memories as memories.
추억은 추억으로 남기죠.
Now, this time...
-자, 요번에는요. -네.
The person with the ID, Give Me Your Boyfriend, sent us a story.
아이디 '남친내놔'님께서 보내주신 사연인데요.
ShinTak couple and Peachy couple were both so loving.
신탁 커플과 피치 커플 둘 다 넘나 애틋했습니다.
Would I be able to fall in love like these couples?
저도 이들처럼 사랑할 수 있을까요?
Goblin, if you're going to leave me, give me a boyfriend!
도깨비 떠날 거면 남친이나 내놔요!
She used Eun Tak's line, "Give me my boyfriend" in her story.
네, 이 분은요 남친을 내놓으라던 그 은탁이 대사로 사연을 보내주셨어요.
That's right. But we can't come up with a boyfriend for you.
그렇습니다, 근데 저희가 그 남친을 만들어 드릴 순 없잖아요?
That's impossible.
그건 불가능한 일이니까
So, we will recall our beautiful love story of Goblin couple instead.
대신해서 저희 도깨비 커플의 아름다운 사랑이야기를 소환해 드리겠습니다.
Yes, someone who created the Goblin couple and was always concerned for them and has watched over them...
네,네 도깨비 부부를 직접 점지하고 늘 걱정하며 지켜봐 온
Someone very special. She'll personally tell us the story.
아주 특별한 분이 직접 이야기를 들려주신다고 하네요.
Then, are Gong Yoo and Kim Go Eun's parents coming out?
어, 그러면 공유씨랑 김고은씨의 부모님들이 나오셔서?
Who could it be? Why don't we meet the person right away?
누가 나올까요 과연,  자 바로 만나보시죠.
[Love Story Recall]
러브 스토리 소환
[A special person visiting the studio]
녹음실로 찾아온 특별한 분
[Samshin Grandma, Lee El]
삼신 할머니 역 이엘
There's a special child that I have created.
내가 점지한 특별한 아이가 있다.
When I created you, I was happy.
너 점지할 때 행복했거든.
All children are special, but Eun Tak made me feel especially happy.
모든 아이가 특별하지만 특히 나를 더 행복하게 했던 은탁이.
The year Eun Tak turned 19 years old...
은탁이가 열아홉살이 되던 해
In front of that child who was desperately making a wish, one man appeared.
간절하게 소원을 비는 그 아이앞에 한 남자가 나타났어.
Was it you?
너야?
This child also is the child I created 939 years ago, Kim Shin.
이, 아이 역시 내가 939년 전에 점지한 아이, 김 신.
Only the Goblin Bride will be able to pull that sword out of you.
오직 도깨비 신부만이 그 검을 뽑을 것이다.
When the sword is taken out, you will return to nothing and will find peace.
검을 뽑으면 무로 돌아가 평안하리라.
He was killed by the sword of the king he used to serve.
자신이 모시던 주군의 칼에 죽임당했지만
But the God gave him an immortal life whether that may be a reward or punishment.
신은 그에게 상인지 벌인지 모를 불멸의 삶을 주었지.
I'm still alive like this and have not been at peace.
나는 여태 이렇게 살아있고, 편안하지 못하였네.
- Ahjussi, are you a Goblin by any chance? - Who are you?
-아저씨 혹시 도깨비 아니에요? -너 뭐야?
It's a bit awkward to say this with my own lips, but I'm the Goblin Bride.
내 입으로 말하긴 좀 뭐한데, 전 도깨비 신부거든요.
I love you.
사랑해요.
After several hundred years, he finally met the Goblin Bride.
몇백 년을 돌아 드디어 도깨비 신부를 만난거야.
As if destined, Eun Tak also fell instantly for Kim Shin.
은탁이도 운명처럼 순식간에 김신에게 빠져버렸지.
Can you... really see it?
너 정말 보여?
This sword.
이 검!
Now I can end this tiresome immortal life. I'm a bit relieved, but it wasn't always so tiresome.
이제 이 지겨운 불멸을 끝낼 수 있구나 다행이다 싶기도 하고 뭐 맨날 지겹진 않았는데..
I do kind of want to live.
아직 더 살아보자 싶기도 하고.
Kim Shin was happy to meet the bride he's been waiting for so long.
김신은 오랫동안 기다려온 신부를 만나 기쁘기도
He also felt bittersweet about the thought of having to end his life.
이제 삶을 끝내야 한다는 생각에 씁쓸하기도 했어.
Do you want to live long? Even though you're the only one who's stuck and everyone else has gone away?
넌 오래 살고 싶어? 너만 멈춰있고 다 흘러가버려도.
You'll be here, Ahjussi. Since you'll continue to be around, I think I'll be okay about living a long time.
아저씨 있잖아요. 아저씨 계속 있을거니까 전 오래 살아도 좋을것 같은데?
Ahjussi!
아저씨!
My heart kept doing the dizzying pendulum motion from heaven to earth.
심장이 하늘에서 땅까지 아찔한 진자운동을 계속하였다.
It was my first love.
첫사랑이었다.
And he began to feel the emotions of first love toward Eun Tak.
그리고 어느새 은탁이에게 첫사랑의 감정을 느끼게 되어버렸지.
♬ You, on the way back  ♬
♬ You, on the way back  ♬
Ahjussi, do you love me?
아저씨, 저 사랑해요?
If you need that, let's do that, too.
그게 필요하면 그거까지 하고.
I love you.
사랑해.
[Before his feelings got much deeper, Kim Shin...]
김신은 이 마음이 더 깊어지기 전에
[Before his attachment to his life gets bigger...]
생에 대한 미련이 커지기 전에
[He wanted to have his sword taken out and end his immortal life.]
검을 뽑고 불멸의 삶을 끝내려 했어.
♬  I’ll certainly recognize you ♬
♫ 꼭 알아볼게 ♫
I should disappear.
난 사라져야 겠다.
Ending this life...
이 생을 끝내는 것.
♬ Even at a place without you... ♬
♫ 니가 없는 곳에서도 ♫
[The day they decided to pull the sword out, Eun Tak couldn't hold onto the sword.]
검을 뽑기로 한 날, 은탁이는 검을 잡지 못했어.
Wait, why can't I hold onto it? I think this is it. I know it.
아니, 이게 왜 안 잡히지? 이거 그건거 같아요 저 알아요.
- What? - A kiss.
-뭔데? -입맞춤이요.
In order to hold onto the sword, even deeper love was necessary...
검을 잡으려면 더 깊은 사랑이 필요했지.
In any case...
어찌됐든
It's nice to be back.
돌아오니 좋구나.
Kim Shin was happy inside...
김 신은 내심 기뻐했어.
He wanted to stay with Eun Tak even for one more day...
은탁이 곁에 하루라도 더 있고 싶었거든.
But Kim Shin soon started feeling great pain in his chest where the sword was stuck.
하지만 곧 김 신은 검이 꽂힌 가슴에 큰 통증을 느꼈어.
What's wrong? Does it hurt? Is it because of the sword?
왜요? 아파요? 혹시 검 때문에 그래요?
Ahjussi... [At last, Eun Tak got to hold the sword]
아저씨
I can hold the sword.
검이 잡혀요!
Wait just a moment. I'll pull it out.
잠깐만 기다려요, 내가 빼줄게요!
Unbeknown to himself, Kim Shin pushed away Eun Tak, who was trying to pull out the sword, with great strength.
김 신은 자기도 모르게 검을 뽑으려던 은탁이를 엄청난 힘으로 밀어버렸어.
Eun Tak became curious after experiencing this.
이 일을 겪은 은탁이는 궁금해했어.
What will happen if she pulls out Kim Shin's sword...
김 신의 검을 뽑으면 대체 어떤 일이 일어나는지.
What happens if I pull out the sword?
검을 뽑으면 어떻게 되는거에요?
Someone to end the Goblin's immortal life. The tool of extinction.
도깨비의 불멸을 끝낼 소멸의 도구.
So, if I pull that sword out...
그러니까 제가 그 검을 빼면
Ahjussi will die?
아저씨가 죽는다구요?
And in front of Eun Tak, a shadow of death kept drawing toward her.
그리고 이런 은탁이 앞엔 자꾸만 죽음의 그림자가 드리워지고 있었어.
It was heartbreaking, but I had to get in the middle of their love for the sake of my children...
마음 아팠지만, 내 아이들을 위해 이들의 사랑에 개입할 수 밖에 없었지.
Hurry up and pull that sword out. Pull it out and exist no longer.
빨리 그 검 뽑다, 검 뽑고 무로 돌아가.
If you don't pull the sword out, death will find that child continuously. I'm sure it's already happened several times.
검을 안빼면 그 아이 앞에 자꾸 죽음이 닥쳐올거야. 이미 여러번 그랬을걸?
What the heck? Stay still!
뒤질려고?!
It will get worse. More often than accidents that have happened before, with more intensity.
앞으론 더 할 거야. 지금까지 있었던 사고들보다 더 자주 점점 세게.
Kim Shin, who is a strong child, was confused for a moment, but...
강한 이 아이 김신은 잠시 혼란스러워했지만
he was changing up the variables in God's plan and enduring miraculously one day at a time.
기특하게도 신의 계획에 변수를 만들어가며 하루하루를 기적으로 버텨가고 있었어.
Human desperation can open any doors and...
인간의 간절함은 못 여는 문이 없고
at times, could one of the doors that open up be a variable in God's plan?
때론 그 열린 문 하나가 신의 계획에 변수가 되는건 아닐까.
I don't know how many times I've gone to hell within an hour.
한 시간 상간에 지옥을 몇 번을 오갔는지 모르겠다.
Wouldn't it be nice if their happiness lasted forever this way...
이들의 행복이 이대로 영원하면 얼마나 좋았을까.
Slowly, the end to their love was nearing.
서서히 이들의 사랑에 끝이 다가오고 있었어.
Good to meet you. You must be the Goblin Bride.
반갑다, 네가 그 도깨비 신부구나.
The purpose of this sword is...
이 검의 효용가치는 결국..
That was it. To take down Park Joong Hun.
그거였어, 박중원을 베는 것.
In order to cut the chord with Park Joong Hun who was threatening Eun Tak's life, Kim Shin...
김 신은 사랑하는 은탁이의 목숨까지 위협하는 박중원과의 악연을 끝으려면
had to borrow Eun Tak's hands to pull out the sword from his body.
은탁이의 손을 빌려 몸에 꽂힌 검을 뽑아야만 했지.
It was unfortunate, but I could only stand by and watch their parting...
안타깝지만 이들의 이별을 지켜볼 수 밖에 없었어.
Having met you in my life... you're my prize.
널 만난 내 생은 상이었다.
Kim Shin suddenly disappeared like this right in front of Eun Tak's eyes...
이렇게 김 신은 은탁이의 눈 앞에서 홀연히 사라졌고
Remember... I must remember... His name was Kim Shin...
기억해, 기억해야돼, 그 사람 이름은 김 신이야.
Eun Tak tried everything to remember that moment...
은탁이는 그 순간을 붙잡으려 몸부림 쳤지만
But in the end, she lost all the memories of him.
결국 모든 기억은 지워지고 말았지.
Between life and death, between light and darkness...
저승과 이승 사이, 빛과 어둠 사이.
In a place where even God is no longer, he was trapped in a state of immortality.
신 조차 떠난 그 곳에 영원불멸 갇히고 말았지.
Kim Shin who returned to nothing, he chose to get caught up in between life and death in order to get back to Eun Tak.
무로 돌아간 김신은 은탁이에게 다시 가기 위해
Eun Tak who lost her memory was in deep pain due to sadness not knowing why...
기억을 잃은 은탁이는 이유조차 알 수 없는 슬픔에 많이 아파했어.
Whose face am I to forget? And forget what promise?
어떤 얼굴을 잊고 무슨 약속을 잊어
Someone please save me.
누가 저 좀 살려주세요.
One day after nine years had passed...
그렇게 9년의 세월이 흐른 어느 날.
Eun Tak's desperate heart was heard by Kim Shin.
은탁이의 애타는 마음이 김신에게 전해졌고
Their desperate longing for each other finally found each other.
둘의 지독한 그리움이 마침내 서로를 찾아냈어.
Although Eun Tak didn't recognize Kim Shin at first,
처음에 은탁이는 김신을 알아보지 못했지만
her feelings beyond the memories started to waver.
기억 저 너머에 있는 감정들이 요동치기 시작했어.
Is your name... Kim Shin?
혹시 이름이 김신이에요?
Ten years ago, you came here with me. Am I correct?
10년전에 나랑 여기 왔었고, 맞아요?
And, at last, at a place where the memories of them together remained,
그리고 이내 둘만의 추억이 깃든 곳에서
a door of the forgotten memories opened.
잊었던 기억의 문도 열리게 되었어.
I miss you!
보고싶어!
♬   Wherever you are. Whatever you look like. I’ll certainly recognize you   ♬
♫ 모습이 어떻든 꼭 알아볼게 ♫
Will you become the bride of this Goryeo man?
이 고려 남자의 신부가 되어줄래?
♬   I’ll remember ♬
♫ 내가 꼭 기억할게 ♫
These two who met after being apart for so long promised a beautiful future together, but...
오랜 이별 끝에 다시 만난 이 아이들은 아름다운 앞날을 약속했지만
♬   Even at a place without you, even if many years pass by  ♬
♫ 니가 없는 곳에서도 ♫
Unfortunately, this happiness didn't last long either.
안타깝게도 이번 행복도 그리 오래가지는 못했어.
Death came at the most perfect moment.
가장 완벽한 순간에 찾아온 죽음.
In the next life, I will be born full of life and
다음 생엔 꼭 생명 가득하게 태어나서
stay for a long, long time by your side.
오래 오래 당신곁에 있을게요.
After leaving her promise to come back,
다시 오겠다는 약속을 남긴 채
Eun Tak left.
은탁이는 떠났고
♫ I did not know before I had you ♫
♫ 널 품기 전 알지 못했다 ♫
Their long waiting began once again.
또 다시 이들의 긴 기다림이 시작됐어.
♫ The world I stay ♫
♫ 내 머문 세상 이토록 ♫
♫ Brilliant ♫
♫ 찬란한 것을 ♫
Another 30 years later...
그렇게 또 30년의 세월이 지나
I found you.
찾았다.
Mister, you know who I am, right?
아저씨 나 누군지 알죠?
My first and last... Goblin's bride.
내 처음이자 마지막 도깨비 신부.
Kim Shin and Eun Tak that met again after a lifetime.
이렇게 생을 한 번 지나 다시 만난 김신과 은탁이.
Just as human choices can become God's variables...
인간의 선택이 신의 변수가 되듯
In this lifetime, no matter what crisis may come...
이번 생에는 어떤 위기가 와도
I wish they stay by each other for a very long time and live brilliantly...
서로의 곁에 오래 머무르며 찬란하기를.
So we saw the love story of Shin Tak couple.
신탁커플의 사랑이야기를 만나보셨는데,
From a God's point of view? Granny?
전지적 신?
It feels new watching it from her view.
할매? 시점으로 보니까 또 새롭네요.
- There is a quite huge age gap between these two, you know. - Yes.
-이 두 분은 나이차이가 꽤 나잖아요. -네.
There is a 12-year gap, but they were like friends, like siblings
띠동갑 커플임에도 불구하고 현장에서는 정말 무슨 친구같이,
at the shooting sight. - Right. A lovey-dovey Kkaemi couple.
-오누이같이. -예, 아주 깨볶는 깨미커플이였어요.
So, we have behind-the-scenes for this couple.
그래서 두 배우의 촬영장 비하인드가 또 준비되어 있습니다.
Those moments that a lot of people have wanted and waited for,
정말 정말 많은 분들이 바라고 염원하셨던
let's watch them right now.
두 분들의 비하인드 한 번 바로 만나보시죠.
[Fate] ♬  It's a beautiful life ♬
♬  It's a beautiful life
Aren't you the Goblin?
아저씨 혹시 도깨비 아니에요?
I love you.
사랑해요.
[Behind the scenes for Shin Tak couple]
♫ 너의 미소도 ♫
Because I got to work with Gong Yoo Sunbaenim,
공유 선배님과 함께한 시간들이여서
I think it was more enjoyable.
더 즐거웠던 것 같습니다.
Just like it's scripted...
마치 짠 것 처럼.
Say something to each other?
서로에게 한마디..
Yo~
요~
Let's be nice.
좋게 갑시다.
We're the same age... [They share the same Chinese zodiac sign]
저희가 동갑이거든요, 네.
Perfect chemistry that's extremely hard to come by?
어지간해서 보기 힘든 찰떡 호흡?
- Right, Go Eun? (friendly) - Yes! (very formal)
-그치 고은아? -네!
Ayoo, what was that?
어유, 왜?
- You should say "Ji Cheol". (his real name) - Aigoo.
-지철아 해야지? -아이고.
[Shin Tak capturing the moment in the maple nation]
단풍국 인증 남기는 신🤍탁
How did it come out?
어떻게 나왔어요?
♬ Only your voice is heard loudly above everything ♬
♫ 너의 목소리만 넘나 크게 들려 ♫
My face looks very small. (satisfied)
오, 내 얼굴이 되게 작게 나왔네?
(Irritated!) It's because you pushed your head back.
뒤로 가니까 그렇지!
I didn't, I just leaned against the bench. It was you that leaned forward.
뒤로 간게 아니라, 기대 앉았을 뿐이야! 네가 앞으로 간거고.
Lean forward, Sunbae!
앞으로 가요!
♬ I can only see your eyes ♬
♫ 너의 눈동자만 넘나 크게 보여 ♫
[One more shot with a different view!]
배경 바꿔서 다시 한 번!
You are taking it from there this time, right? [!!!!!!]
♫ 아니 내가 정말 미친걸까 ♫
♬ Since I only think of you all day ♬
♫ 하루종일 너만 생각하다 보니  ♫
You can't do that.
안 되지!
[It's still nice to see this Shin Tak couple even if they argue]
♫ 머리가 이상해진 것 같아 ♫
♬ Is it perhaps that I came to like you? ♬
♫ 혹시 내가 너를 좋아하게 돼버린 걸까 ♫
[Give me some snack, too.]
나도 과자 줘~
They squabbled over nothing a lot, but
진짜 티격태격 많이 하면서
- But they look after each other a lot. - Yes, they're very caring.
-서로를 얼마나 아끼는지. -서로 근데 얼마나 챙겨줬는데.
[Squirm, squirm]
꼼지락 꼼지락
[Eun Tak gives him a cookie]
과자 찔끔 주는 은탁이
[How petty...]
도깨비 치사 빤쓰...
We must look so pathetic...
진짜 얼마나, 얼마나 옹색해 보이겠냐, 이거.
[It tastes good though.]
그래도 맛은 있구나...
So what...
먹긴 먹었네요 그래도.
[Eun Tak inhaled helium instead of the snack]
과자 대신 헬륨 먹은 은탁이
Hello. This is Eun Tak.
안녕하세요~ 은탁이에요.
We have a few days left. I feel sad. You feel the same, right?
이제 며칠 안 남았네요. 너무 아쉬워요. 여러분도 그렇죠?
[Found him!] Ah, Sunbae.
아, 선배님!
It's not good for you if you inhale that too much.
자상한
Even if it's not good for me, it's not like I do this every day. [Eun Tak is happy with a mere balloon. Cuteness overload.]
안 좋아도 뭐 제가 매일 매일 마시나요.
I inhale once in a while.
상황극 연출 중
You and I can stand like this... [Trying to produce a scene]
너하고 규태가 저 쪽에서 팔짱끼고 연행하는 것처럼
Someone should join from there. That's right, you should hold the mic.
여기서 한 명 더 들어와야지, 그렇지 마이크 들어야지.
Right, you should ask questions, too.
그렇지 질문 던지면서.
I have nothing to say. I don't remember. [Criminal that stole the Goblin's heart]
드릴 말씀이 없습니다, 생각이 나지 않습니다.
I don't know. [They must be tired since it's almost the end of the project but still trying to cheer everyone up]
저는 모릅니다.
One, two, three.
하나,둘,셋
Goblin, fighting!
도깨비 파이팅!
[Lovey-dovey Shin Tak couple until the end]
끝까지 애정 돋는 신💓탁 커플
Ah, it's really funny, right?
-정말 -정말 재밌다.
Yes. The chemistry of these two is one of the best. [Kim Shin
-그죠? -이 두분의 케미는 손 꼽는 것같아요.
Gong Yoo took good care of Go Eun.
공유씨가 고은이를 많이 챙겨주고
- Of course. - And Go Eun respected Gong Yoo sunbae as well, calling him Sunbae.
-그럼요. -고은씨도 공유선배를 아주 '선배,선배'하면서 잘 따르고
Yeah, that's right. It makes me feel pleased and content.
응, 맞아요 괜히 흐뭇하고 즐겁고 그렇습니다.
We should move on. [Who's the next couple?]
-다음으로 가봐야죠. -네, 네.
The sad love of these two, Goblin and Grim Reaper.
도깨비와 저승사자 두 분의 애절한 사랑.
Don't you think it's our show's highlight? Bromance?
저희 드라마의 최대 관전 포인트 아니겠어요? 브로맨스.
[Bromance. Goblin
브로맨스 도깨비💗저승사자
[So here it is.]
그래서 준비했습니다.
[We can't take our eyes off of this charming couple.]
눈을 뗄 수 없는 마성의 커플
Goblin?
도깨비?
Grim Reaper?
저승사자?
You want to try getting into a fight with the Goblin?
도깨비와 얼굴 붉히는 우를 범해 보시겠다?
I'm sure you're well aware of what the contract with the Grim Reaper means.
사자와의 계약이 어떤건지 잘 알텐데?
[The real chemistry of Goblin and Grim Reaper?]
현실 속 도깨비💖저승사자의 케미는?
[Real bromance 1: Show me the Reaper]
도깨비💘저승사자의 현실 브로맨스 1
Action.
큐!
So what? Isn't that good?
근데, 그럼 잘된 것 아니야?
Weren't you looking for a br-
죽기 위해...
[Tongue tied. NG]
발음이 꼬여 NG
So what? Isn't that good? Weren't you looking for a bride to die?
아, 근데 그럼 잘된 것 아니야? 죽기 위해 신부 찾고 있었던 것 아니였어?
The bride... that would... return you to nothing...
너를 무로 돌아가게 해줄...
[Swag] The bride that would return you to nothing.
너를 무로 돌아가게 해줄.
We will try again.
들어가겠습니다.
So what? Isn't that good?
아, 근데 그럼 잘된거 아니야?
Weren't you looking for a bride to die? The bride that will ret- $#^#
죽기 위해 신부 찾고 있었던거 아니였어? 너를 무로 돌아..
[Aigoo]
아이고
[Grim Reaper's excuses]
아, 이게
"The bride that will return you to nothing." Every phrase has the "r" sound, that's why...
-와, 저러기 시작하면.. -너를 무로 돌아가게 해줄 이게 다 'ㄹ'발음이 있어가지고
The bride that will return you to nothing.
너를 무로 돌아가게 해 줄
I couldn't do it well. [Embarrassed]
어, 잘 안되더라고요 발음이.
I mean,
왜
why would you add grooves?
왜 리듬을 타?
Even if you are so happy because there is no shooting schedule for you tomorrow...
아무리 신나도, 내일 촬영이 없어도
I'm sorry.
아, 죄송합니다.
My tongue keeps... My tongue keeps getting tied. The bride that will return you to nothing.
이게 발음이 계속, 계속 돌려서.. 너를.무로.돌아.가게.해줄...
[Work well, tongue TT]
하...
The bride that will return you to nothing...
너를, 너를 무로 돌아가게 해줄.
[You should be on Show Me the Money~]
쇼미더머니 나가도 되겠어~
I'm sorry!
죄송합니다.
[We are the hip hoppers!]
우리가 힙합 전도사.
[DAP!]
DAP!
Ho! Ho! Ho!
호우! 호우! 호우!
Around this time.. [Sorry, we will hurry up and shoot.]
-이 시간쯤 되면... -빨리 찍을게.
Dong Wook and I are always like this. Trying to keep us awake.
-동욱이랑 나랑 항상 이런거 같아, 어. -잠 깨려고.
Get up.
다음 씬 일어나야돼.
Look, look, look at me.
봐바, 봐바.
[Real bromance 2: Charades]
도깨비💓저승사자의 현실 브로맨스 2
[This looks familiar?]
안절부절
- Gong Yoo! - Correct!
- 공유. - 맞아, 정답.
A part of me thinks that it's a relief that I can end this tiring immortal life.
이제 이 지겨운 불멸을 끝낼 수 있구나, 다행이다 싶기도 하고.
Then it wasn't always that tiring so I feel like living a little more. [Omg, a human copying machine?]
뭐 맨날 지겹진 않았는데, 아직 더 살아보자 싶기도
[Give it a try to guess, you viewers~]
시청자 여러분도 맞혀보세요~
The foot of the lamp is dark. ("The husband is always the last to know.")
오, 등잔 밑이 어둡다?
[Second question!]
빠르게 두 번째 문제!
Okay, needle.
그래 바늘.
[The answer for Gong Yoo's question will be out shortly.]
잠시 후 공유의 몸으로 말해요 정답이 공개됩니다.
[Second question!] Okay, needle.
빠르게 두번째 문제
"He that steals a needle, will steal an ox."
바늘도둑이 소도둑 된다고.
You and I will be the only ones featured in the "Makings of..."
메이킹은 너랑 나랑 둘밖에 없다.
Of us always acting like fools.
이렇게 둘이 맨날 삼돌이 짓하고.
[Real bromance 3: Memories resemble love]
오~
What are you looking at? [Grim Reaper, deeply immersed in a childhood cartoon]
뭐 봐?
[Of course, this Goblin full of joyful spirit cannot pass.]
역시 그냥 지나치지 않는 흥깨비
Shouldn't we do this, too? At times when you use the sword and stuff...
우리도 이렇게 해야 되는거 아니야? 검쓰고 막 이럴때?
[Happy 9-year old, not 900]
세상 신 난 9짤
Do this.
이거 봐, 얘네 막.
[Happy, Happy]
해맑 해맑
[Just with one animation, the Goblin and the Grim Reaper are having so much fun.]
열심히 하잖아.
We can watch Dragon Ball, Dragon Ball.
드래곤볼 때 보면 돼.
[Transformed!] [Ta Da]
짜잔!
We are not watching this for fun, never.
이게 절대 보고싶어서 보는게 아닙니다.
We are studying so we can use this when we act.
우리 그 마법 쓸 때, 공부하려고.
As a reference...
참고자료.
That's right, as a reference.
맞아요 참고자료 였어요.
Really? For real? [Would you look at my eyes?]
진짜? 정말로요?
Honestly, I wanted to see it.
보고 싶었어요.
Average age 37.
평균 나이 37세
Almost 40.
내일 모레 40.
It's just we are captured by memories.
추억에 젖는거지.
[Real bromance 4: Discovery of a new item?]
도깨비💓저승사자의 현실 브로맨스  4
Let me try. Oh, it's in English.
해봐야지, 오우씨 나 이거 영어로 돼있네?
[What are they doing?]
두 사람이 열중하고 있는 것은?!
I changed it. Look, look. [Goblin Hyung, look!]
내꺼 지금 다썼어, 봐바 봐바.
[Cell phone neon sign app]
봐바.
[ Cell phone neon sign app ]
휴대폰 전광판 어플
[ Heart melted] [Goblin is the best! I will take the sword out!!!]
도깨비 짱! 가슴에 검 빼줄게욧!
He's downloading this. Doesn't he look so serious? He's downloading it.
지금 그거 다운받고 있는거야, 되게 심각해 보이지? 이거 다운받고 있는거야.
[Did it finally work...?]
글씨체가 좀 작은거 아니냐 이거?
[Confused. Left. Right.]
우왕 좌왕
[Quickly]
후다닥
By the way,
여러분!! 감사합니다♡
can you see this through the camera?
이게 카메라에 찍혀?
Of course. [Gong Yoo is worried that the viewers might not be able to see it.]
찍히지!
[Viewers
도깨비 시청자들이 못 볼까봐 걱정하는 공유
The letters got big. Look, look. I have this, too.
어, 커졌네 커졌네. 봐바, 난 이것도 된다~
[The Reaper is showing off.] [Envy. Envy.]
깨알 자랑 중인 저승사자
We should adjust the size. The timing is off.. [The Goblin is sad because the timing is off.]
맞춰야지 사이즈, 에이 안 맞는다.
Then, let's press it together on the count of 3.
그러면 하나둘셋 하면 동시에
Should I change the color?
색깔도 바꿔야 돼요?
Oh, the blinking effect works.
어, 깜빡거리는거 돼.
Oh, right, right.
어, 그래 그래 그래.
[Viewers!]
시청자 여러분!
[Thank you
감사합니다♡
This blinks.
이거 깜빡인다.
♬  That's how it works   ♬
♬  That's how it works  ♬
[Real Bromance 5: Real love story]
도깨비♡저승사자의 현실 브로맨스 5
Ah, I don't know.
아, 몰라.
Why the sad music? [Bewildered. Embarrassed.]
음악 왜 애절하죠?
What, you feel good because I care about you?
왜 걱정해주니까 좋아?
Yeah, my heart melted.
심쿵했어.
My heart melted earlier, when you did this to me...
아까 나 심쿵했어 네가 이렇게
With your jacket.
어, 이거 이거
When you hugged me with your jacket like this.
무스탕으로 이렇게 안아줬을때.
[Goblin
도깨비♡저승사자의 뷰티풀- 크러시
♬  It's a beautiful life. I’ll be by your side ♬
♫ It`s a beautiful life 난 너의 곁에 있을게  ♫
[How cute]
귀여워
♬ It's a beautiful life. I’ll stand behind you ♬
♫ It`s a beautiful life 너의 뒤에 서 있을게  ♫
Anything looks good in my eyes, I'm telling you.
내 눈엔 다 예쁘다니까? 괜찮아.
I'm fine if I look good in your eyes. Others don't matter.
너 눈에만 괜찮으면 돼. 다른 사람 따윈 필요 없어.
I thought I could have you.
널 가질 수 있을 거라 생각했어.
Because you are my man.
넌 내 남자니까.
♬ It’s good to breathe ♬
♫ 숨쉬는것만으로도 좋아  ♫
[Reaper takes a bite
저승이 한 입♡
[Goblin takes a bite
♫ It`s a beautiful life  ♫
- I'll hold you. - Hug me.
컷, 오케이.
♬ Beautiful life, Beautiful day ♬
♫ Beautiful life beautiful day  ♫
♬ Stay with me ♬
♫ 내 곁에서 머물러줘  ♫
♬ Beautiful my love ♬
♫ beautiful my love   ♫
♬ Beautiful your heart ♬
♫ beautiful your heart  ♫
♬ It's a sorrowful life, sorrowful day  ♬
♫ It`s a sorrowful life sorrowful day  ♫
♬ I cannot overcome sorrow ♬
♫ 슬픔을 이기지 못하는 내게  ♫
♬ Do not leave me by my side ♬
♫ 내 곁에서 떠나지마  ♫
♬ I do not want to live in memory ♬
♫ 추억속에 내가  ♫
Dong Wook, I think I'll think of you often.
동욱 씨, 아마 두고두고도 계속 생각날 것 같은데
I was so happy to work with you in this drama.
같이 드라마해서 너무너무 좋았고
Next time, through another great project...
다음에 또 좋은 작품으로
I'd love to act with you again. I miss you.
같이 연기했음 좋겠습니다. 네, 보고싶구나.
Say something.
한마디 하세요.
- Through this program? - Yes, yes. -  I'm getting nervous.
-이 자리를 빌어서요? 아, 또 괜히 떨리네? -네, 네.
Mr. Goblin... Gong Yoo hyung... Those were fantastic days.
도깨비씨, 공유형 참 찬란한 날들이었습니다.
Thanks to you, I wasn't lonely. If I can work with you again...
덕분에 쓸쓸하지 않았구요. 또 같이 한다면
I think I can do a better job more happily and have more fun doing it.
더 즐겁게 재밌게 잘 할 수 있을것 같아요.
I almost got a bit jealous.
저까지 괜히 조금 질투가 날 뻔 했어요.
Don't be jealous. To me, Sunny is always number one.
질투하지 마세요 그래도 언제나 저에게는 써니 씨가 넘버원이에요.
- Really? - Of course. [Crazy...]
-아, 정말요? -네, 그럼요.
Hello, Goblin fans...
안녕하세요 도깨비 시청자 여러분들!
Right before our last filming...
마지막 촬영을 앞두고
I will show you the filming scene.
촬영 현장을 많이 담아보도록 하겠습니다.
It's my first time seeing the Grim Reaper.
-계속 TV로만 뵙다가. -저승사자는 처음 봤네요.
The promised TT dance for the ratings...
공약 거신 TT를 추신다고.
- Thank you for your love. - Thank you. [Do not change the channel if you want to see more of this lovely shot]
-사랑해주셔서 감사합니다. -감사합니다.
The story of our couple...
우리 커플의 이야기는
Who's going to tell it? Deok Hwa?
그럼 누가 들려주나요? 덕화가 들려주나?
That would be good, too, but...
아, 뭐 그것도 좋겠지만
we're here. Is another person necessary?
우리가 여기 있는데 뭐 다른 사람이 들려줄 필요가 있을까요?
Yes, I do think that may be necessary. [Answering without hesitation]
네, 그럴 필요도 있을것 같은데.
- It's a bit embarrassing to talk about us. - No, we don't need it.
-저희가 저희 얘기 하긴 좀 쑥쓰러우니까. -아니야, 아니야, 필요없어.
- We don't need it? - Yeah, we don't need it.
아, 필요없어요? 네, 알겠습니다.
Since we're here...
-단호하시네요. -이번에는 저희가 있으니까
we will tell you directly.
저희가 직접 들려드리도록 할게요.
You lived well in this life.
이 생에서 수고 많았어요
Drink it. It will erase all the memories of this life.
마셔요, 이승의 기억을 잊게 해줍니다.
I am the Grim Reaper.
저는 저승사자 입니다.
How much is this?
이거 얼마에요?
- Crying? - One day, I met a woman and...
울어? 어느날 저는 한 여자를 보고
and cried tears without knowing why.
이유 모를 눈물을 흘렸습니다.
I'm Sunny.
써니에요.
She gave me her phone number, but...
그녀는 제게 전화번호를 주었지만
I don't have the courage to call her.
차마 연락할 용기가 나지 않습니다.
Why isn't he calling me?
그는 왜 연락을 하지 않는 걸까요?
Is my beauty fading these days? He should've called me a long time ago.
나 요즘 미모 비수기니? 분명 이 쯤엔 연락 오고도 남았는데.
I met him only once...
딱 한 번 만났을 뿐인데
but I couldn't forget him.
그가 계속 잊혀지지 않아
I waited for him in vain.
하염없이 그를 기다렸습니다.
Is this a coincidence?
이거 우연이에요?
Not for me. Why didn't you call me? I waited for it. You said you'd call.
난 아니에요. 왜 전화 안했어요? 기다렸는데, 한다면서요!
I will. I'll go now and call.
하겠습니다. 가서 지금.
This man... he cried the first time I saw him...
이 남자, 처음 봤을 땐 갑자기 눈물을 흘리더니
Now that we meet again, he doesn't say anything.
다시 만난 지금은 아무 말도 안 하네요?
Aren't we going to say how we're doing? Aren't we going to talk?
인사 안해요 우리? 안부 안 묻구요? 얘기는 안 하나요?
How am I doing? Someone who's not alive?
살아있지 않은 자에게 안부라니.
My real name is one syllable.
내 진짜 이름은 외자에요.
Kim Seon.
김 선.
Kim Woo Bin,
김우빈씨
what's your real name?
진짜 이름은 뭐에요?
In any case, I from the dead and Sunny from the living...
어짜피 저승의 저와 이승의 써니 씨는
We were not meant to be.
이루어질 수 없는 운명이였죠.
- Look carefully. - I can't tell. I'll know when I touch her hand.
-잘 좀 봐. - 그냥 봐서 몰라. 손이 닿아야 알아.
What happens when you touch her hand?
아니 손 닿으면 뭘 아는데요?
If I touch someone's hand...
저는 누군가의 손을 잡으면
I can see that person's past life.
그 사람의 전생을 볼 수 있습니다.
The day I accidently held her hand...
우연히 그녀의 손을 잡게 된 날
I saw her past life.
그녀의 전생을 보았습니다.
She was...
그녀는
the one I had seen in a portrait not long ago...
얼마 전, 제가 초상화 속에서 본
Kim Shin's younger sister.
김 신의 여동생이였고
Amazingly...
신기하게도 전
when I saw that portrait...
그 초상화를 보고도
I cried not knowing why.
알 수 없는 눈물을 흘렸었죠.
Why did I cry?
나 왜 울었지?
What's behind my emotions?
내 감정의 정체는 뭐지?
Is it relevant to my erased memory?
내 지워진 기억이 관련이 있는걸까?
I heard you become a Grim Reaper if you commit a grave sin in your lifetime.
전생에 큰 죄를 지으면 저승사자가 된다는데
What and how grave of a sin could you have committed?
대체 무슨 죄를 얼마나 크게 지은 걸까요?
Could it be that I committed a grave sin in her past life?
제가 그녀의 전생에서 큰 죄를 지은건 아닐까요?
I wanted to see her past life once more.
그녀의 전생을 한 번 더 보고 싶어졌습니다.
I'm sorry for running late. I'll hold your hand.
-늦어서 미안해요! 손 좀 잡겠습니다. -응?
Right away like this?
이렇게 바로요?
I'm too curious to have to wait.
기다리기엔 제가 너무 궁금해서요.
You still haven't answered my question.
아직 제 질문에 대답 안해줬잖아요.
Who are you exactly, Kim Woo Bin?
정체가 뭐냐구요 김우빈씨.
Who is this man exactly?
이 남자의 정체는 대체 뭘까요?
Who he is...
그는 자신이 누군지
He didn't reveal it to me.
끝내 제게 밝히지 않네요.
Is it too much for me to ask?
너무 무리한 요구에요?
I'm sorry.
미안합니다.
Then, should we just end it here? I'll just get dumped.
그럼 그만 할까요 우리? 그냥 내가 차일게요.
Don't call me from now on.
앞으로 연락하지 마세요.
If I said goodbye, I thought he might change his attitude.
이별을 말하면 그의 태도가 변할까 했지만
But he didn't even hold on to me and just accepted my goodbye.
그는 저를 잡지도 않고 이별을 받아들이네요.
Did he even like me at all?
저를 좋아하긴 한걸까요?
Did I dump her or...
그녀가 차였는가
did she dump me?
내가 차였는가
I loved her, but...
그녀를 사랑하지만
I couldn't hold onto her.
차마 잡을 수 없었습니다.
Before she struggles more...
그녀가 더 힘들어하기 전에
Before I hurt her even more...
그녀에게 더 큰 상처를 주기 전에.
I decided to say goodbye to her...
그녀와 이별하기로 마음먹고
To give back her ring...
반지를 돌려주러
I went to her store.
그녀의 가게로 찾아갔습니다.
Is he about this tall?
대략 이 높이인가?
And in the end...
그리고 결국
she caught me.
그녀에게 들켜버렸습니다.
The fact that I'm the Grim Reaper.
제가 저승사자인것을.
That's who you are...
이게 정체였구나.
I knew it couldn't be...
안될 줄 알면서
but I dreamed of a happy ending.
해피엔딩을 꿈꿨습니다.
But as expected...
하지만 역시
it's a tragedy.
비극이네요.
Shall we...
우리 그만
just say goodbye?
헤어질까요?
That man is the Grim Reaper. Are there any obsessive female ghosts who come looking for him?
그 남자 저승사자더라? 막 찾아오고 집착하는 여자귀신 같은건 없니?
That was my first thought.
그 생각부터 들더라.
Even after I found out his identity...
그의 정체를 알고나서도
my feelings toward him didn't change.
그의 대한 마음은 변하지 않았습니다.
The kiss of a Grim Reaper...
저승사자의 키스는
brings back memories of past life.
전생을 기억나게 합니다.
In my past life, he was my love...
그는 전생에 저의 사랑이자
and pain.
아픔이었네요.
The things I saw...
내가 본 것들
What was that?
뭐에요?
By chance...
혹시
In your past life...
당신의 전생속에
Am I in it?
나도 있나요?
Even in the past life...
전생에서도 제가 그녀를
I think I hurt her.
아프게 했던 것 같습니다.
Except for the happiest moments...
행복으로 반짝거리던 순간들만 남기고
Difficult and...
힘들고
sad moments...
슬픈 순간들은
Forget all of it.
다 잊어요.
And...
그리고
Forget me, too.
나도 잊어요.
Even if it's only you...
당신만은
I wish you a happy ending even like this...
이렇게라도 해피엔딩이길.
♬ I’ll certainly find you ♬
♫ 내가 꼭 찾아낼게 ♫
♬ I’ll recognize you ♬
♫ 내가 널  알아볼게 ♫
While carrying out your duty...
그대는 차사직을 수행함에 있어
we confirmed that you used your powers for personal reasons.
사사로히 능력을 쓴 사실이 확인되었다.
No...
허니...
Face your sins again.
다시 너의 죄와 대면하라
Since then, for violating heaven's laws...
그 이후, 저는 하늘의 법을 어긴 죄로
I was punished by remembering the sins of my past life.
전생의 죄를 기억하는 벌을 받게 됐습니다.
That ring, I...
내가 그 반지를
I put it on her so brutally.
그렇게 못되게 끼웠어.
On her finger...
그녀의 손에.
It was me who hurt her...
그녀를 아프게 하고,
and killed her...
죽게 한게 나였다니
The memories that flooded in agonized me.
몰려오는 기억에 고통스러웠습니다.
Thankfully, I erased all of her painful memories.
다행히 그녀의 아팠던 기억들은 이미 다 지웠으니
All the painful...
그녀는 아프기만했던
You told me to remember just the happy moments and forget you. That's not the correct order.
행복했던 순간들만 남기래 놓고 당신을 잊으라니 순서가 안 맞지.
All the moments you were there... including sad and difficult moments and all...
당신이 있는 모든 순간이 슬프고 힘들었던 것 조차 다.
They were all good to me.
그조차도 나는 다 좋았네요.
My memories with him did not disappear at all.
그와의 기억이 하나도 지워지지 않았습니다.
Even the difficult moments... during the time I spent with him, everything was happy to me.
힘들었던 순간조차, 그와 함께했던 시간들은 모두가 행복이었나 봅니다.
Let's really break up. Goodbye, Your Majesty.
진짜 헤어져요 우리. 굿바이 폐하.
But he who caused so much pain in my past life... I don't think I could love him again.
하지만 전생에 나에게 크나큰 아픔을 줬던 그를 이제 다신 사랑할 수 없을 것 같습니다.
Saying goodbye is the only punishment I can give him.
제가 그에게 줄 수 있는 벌이 이별뿐이네요.
Nine years have passed by after having said goodbye to her like that.
그렇게 그녀와 이별하고 9년이란 시간이 흘렀습니다.
Ever since the Goblin returned to nothing... people didn't remember me...
도깨비가 무로 돌아간 후, 사람들은 더 이상 저를 기억하지 못했고
- Your name is? - Wang Yeo.
-성함이? -왕여.
I'm Sunny.
난 써니에요.
It seems Sunny doesn't remember me either now.
써니 씨도 이제 저를 기억하지 못하는 것 같습니다.
I wanted to see you. I saw the CCTV. Since I got to see you in person, I'll get going now.
보고싶었어요. CCTV 봤거든요. 실물 뵀으니 그만 가볼게요.
It was nice to meet you.
만나서 반가웠어요.
She couldn't remember me, but I was happy to have met her like this again.
저를 기억하지 못하는 그녀지만 이렇게라도 다시 만날 수 있어서 기뻤습니다.
It was nice to see you, Kim Woo Bin.
반가웠어 김우빈씨.
Actually, I clearly remembered the memories of my past life and this life with him...
사실 그와 함께했던 전생과 이생의 기억을 그대로 간직하고 있었지만
But I pretended not to remember him.
그를 기억하지 못하는 척 했습니다.
He had me remember my past life and tried to erase it...
전생도 기억나게 했다가 지울려고 했다가
Wouldn't oblivion be God's consideration?
망각은 신의 배려 아닐까요?
It's my memory and my life. How dare he be considerate without even asking me?
내 기억이고 내 인생인데 물어보지도 않고 왜 지맘대로 배려야?
I said I'd live with painful memories of my love... I had told God not to get involved in my life.
가슴 아픈 사랑의 기억을 안고 살겠다고 신에게 더 이상 내 인생에 개입하지 말라고 했거든요.
Hopefully, in the next life...
부디 다음 생에서 우린
we don't have to wait long, but get to spend a long time together...
기다림은 짧고 만남은 긴 인연으로
As a perfect answer to love... I hope we meet like that.
언제나 정답인 사랑으로 그렇게 만나지길 빌어요.
Even though I love him, but can't...
그를 사랑하지만 사랑할 수 없으므로
Again, I will depart to a place where he can't find me.
이제 다시 그가 저를 찾지 못하는 곳으로 떠나려고 합니다.
I'll leave after counting up to 50. 48...
딱 50만 세고 가야지.
He found out that I remembered everything and came to me.
제가 모든 것을 기억하고 있다는 걸 알게 된 그가 저를 찾아와 줬습니다.
♫ I don’t know why my tears keep falling when I look at you ♫
♫ 바라보면 자꾸 ♫
In this lifetime...
이 생에서는...
You won't see me again.
다신 못 볼 거예요.
Like this, we said our last goodbyes again.
이렇게 우리는 또 마지막 인사를 했습니다.
30 years after she left me, one day...
이렇게 그녀를 떠나보내고 30년이 지난 어느 날.
This is the last one.
마지막 명부입니다.
With the news of termination of my punishment of living as a Grim Reaper, I received my list.
이제 저승사자로 사는 긴 벌이 끝났다는 소식과 함께 마지막 명부를 받았습니다.
Her name is listed on the list.
명부엔 그녀의 이름이 적혀있네요.
She said she won't stay in touch... Even this must be our fate.
소식 안 전한다더니 이조차 운명인가 봅니다.
I wanted to put it on you properly for once.
제대로 한 번쯤 끼워 주고 싶었어요.
I felt bad that I put it on you so cruelly.
그렇게 못되게 끼워서 미안했어요.
We ended our lives together like this.
이렇게 우리는 마지막을 함께했습니다.
In our next life, hopefully we will be perfected in love...
다음 생애에선 부디 정답인 사랑으로
I hope we don't have to wait long, but get to spend a long time together...
기다림은 짧고 만남은 긴 인연으로 만나지길.
[Heartbreaking and sad love story, the two cannot continue on...]
애잔하고 슬픈 러브스토리에 한동안 말을 잇지 못한 두 사람...
Actually, I couldn't really date Sunny.
사실 써니와는 제대로 연애를 못 해봤잖아요.
The sweet romance... wasn't quite there.
달달했던 어떤 연애 과정이 좀 없었어요.
Yes, that's right. I was an idiot in the beginning.
응, 맞아요. 초반에는 제가 워낙 바보 같았잖아요. 그러니까 연애를 전혀..
In the beginning?
초반이요?
Was I always?
늘 그랬나요?
I was wondering how it could've been if we had showed the cute and sweet side of our love. But even still, our story...
그래서 그냥 그런 귀엽고 알콩달콩한게 조금 더 보여줬으면 어땠을까 생각도 드는데 그래도 저희의 서사가..
did continue well, so the viewers... [The Grim Reaper and Sunny's love story received lots of viewers' cheers and love]
-네. -이렇게 좀 잘 이어져 와서. 시청자분들도 많이 좀.
- People cheered us on and understood us. - They were loving to us...
-응원해주시고. 이해해주셔서. -애틋하게 봐주셔서.
I was so thankful. Thanks to you, I was able to do a good job. Thanks again.
너무 감사했죠. 덕분에 잘했던거 같아요. 다시 한 번 감사드립니다.
Thank you.
아유, 저도 감사합니다.
Now that we've talked about our story...
그러면은 이제 저희의 얘기를 또
We should take a look at the Peach couple's behind-the-scenes.
했으니까 피치커플의 비하인드도 한 번 봐바야죠?
- Yes, yes. Shall we? - Let's take a look at our behind-the-scenes.
-네, 네 그럴까요? -저희 둘만의 비하인드 어떤지 함께 보시죠.
[Happy ending in this life]
♫ 너 정말 이쁘다 이쁘다  ♫
It's our first day starting today.
오늘부터 우리 1일 이에요.
[Sunny is recording the scene where she falls in shock hearing a phone ringing on an overpass where no one is around]
♫ 왜 말하고 말하고  ♫
[Geez]
♫ 아무리 말해도 화난 듯한 ♫
You were so awkward falling down...
넘어지는 연기 너무 어색하게 하셔서
- I didn't have to completely fall in this cut. - You really want me to fall and crack my head, huh, Oppa?
아니 넘어지는 거까지 안 쓰는 커트였으니까. 내가 진짜 넘어져서 머리 깨졌으면 좋겠죠, 오빠?
Right, I'd be just watching you like this...
그럼 난 그냥 이렇게 보고 있는거지 저승사자처럼.
- Not saying anything? - Yeah.
아무말도 안하고?
You won't step on me? [You think I'd step on you?]
-안 밟을 거야? -되게.
What do people do on a date at a coffee shop?
커피숍에서 데이트하면 뭐하냐고.
Give me some ideas. I've never been on a date in a coffee shop.
아이디어 좀 줘.
[For no reason, he hits.] You're going to hit me now?
왜 이제 때려?
[Kiss, kiss!]
뽀뽀, 뽀뽀.
- It was in the script. - You said you won't do it.
-대본에 쓰여 있던데? -안 찍는다며.
[I won't do it.] But we ended up kissing, right?
안 할 거야. 결국 했죠 근데?
The reason you shouldn't miss Goblin,
도깨비를 놓치면 안되는 이유.
is the fact that all the actors appearing in the Goblin are all alive?
도깨비에 출연하는 모든 배우들이 하나하나 살아 숨 쉬고 있다는거?
- Because we're not dead. - Hey...
죽은 사람들이 아니니까..
Seriously...
아, 진짜!
- I'm totally working on my image. - Why?
-나 지금 겁나 이미지 트레이닝 중이야. -왜?
I have to do a kiss scene. [Grim Reaper has to do a kiss scene with Sunny]
어? 키스신 연습하려고 이미지 트레이닝.
[Excited, excited] [Practicing the kiss scene by himself]
언제?
Huh?
어?
Shouldn't the Grim Reaper be a bad kisser? Good thing you're doing it.
저승은 키스 잘 못해야 맞는거 아니야?
[Awkward, like this?] No, not like that.
-그래, 저승은 그렇게. -아니야.
Forget it.
됐어!
But that was the tearful kiss scene.
근데 저거 그 키스신이 잖아, 눈물의 키스신.
- That's right. - We couldn't do it.
-맞아요. -그런거 하나도 못했잖아요.
We couldn't do it. So disappointing. I was so disappointed.
하나도 못했어요 아쉽게. 너무 아쉬웠어.
Sunny... the character is so great. She's so charming.
써니가 캐릭터가 너무 잘잡혀갖고 너무 매력있지 않아요?
I've never seen a character like that before.
진짜 본 적이 없는 캐릭터야.
She's so unique? Wondering, "Who's she?" Makes you keep watching her.
독특하잖아 캐릭터가. '쟤 뭐지?' 약간 이렇게 되는. 계속 보게 되고.
I think In Na approached the character very well.
그게 인나가 또 되게 잘 잡은 거 같아.
We talked a lot about you when you weren't there. Me, Gong Yoo hyung, and Eun Tak.
써니 씨 없을때 저희끼리 얘기 많이 했었어요. 저랑 공유형이랑 뭐 은탁이까지 같이 가가지고
That you approached the character so well. And more than what's written in the script...
캐릭터를 너무 잘잡았고 그리고 대본에 쓰여있는 거보다
your tone was so funny and so tasteful...
톤 자체를 너무 이렇게 재밌게 맛깔나게 해오셔 가지고.
[Thanks, thanks]
아유..
Sit down! Before I kill you.
딱 앉아요, 죽여버리기 전에.
So cute.
귀여워!
I'm so glad you played Sunny, In Na.
써니 씨가 인나 씨여서 참 다행이였던 것 같습니다.
I really thank you.
정말 감사드립니다.
[I was happy to play Sunny, too]
네.
I'll read the next letter.
다음 사연은 제가 한 번 읽어볼게요.
Someone with the ID, Buckwheat Eat Goblin, sent us this letter.
아이디 '메밀 먹깨비'님께서 보내주신 소환 사연입니다.
"I heard you took the story of Goblins from tales. Are Goblins and Grim Reapers in tales this cool?"
도깨비 이야기 설화에서 가져 왔다고 하는데, 설화 속 도깨비, 저승사자도 이렇게 멋짐 터지나요?라고 하셨네요.
Since we don't know too much about this topic, we'll call up the expert and hear from him.
이거는 저희도 잘 모르겠어서, 이 분야의 전문가 선생님을 소환해서 이야기를 들어보도록 하죠.
Okay.
네.
[Recalling Narrative Tale]
설화 소환
We took the motif from the narrative tales.
설화에서 모티브를 가져왔구요
There weren't that many people who researched the subject.
연구하시는 분들이 많지가 않으셔가지고
We used our imagination and made it possible for us to add on to it.
상상 가능했고, 많이 보탤 수가 있었어요.
If the soul lands on an object that has been touched by people or blood...
사람의 손때나 피가 묻은 물건에 염원이 깃들면
you become a Goblin.
도깨비가 된단다.
The drama that took motifs from Goblin fairytales.
도깨비 설화에서 모티브를 가져온 이 드라마.
Up to what portion is it taken from tales and which portion came from the writer's creative writing?
어디까지가 설화 속 이야기고, 어디까지가 작가의 창작일까.
We will take a look one at a time together.
지금부터 저와 함께 하나씩 풀어가 보도록 하겠습니다.
First, the person of interest, the Goblin. Recalling Gong Yoo Goblin.
먼저 첫번째 의문 대상자, 공유 도깨비 소환.
[You can call up the Goblin when you blow out a candle?]
도깨비는 촛불을 불면 소환된다?
Don't you want to call each other on the cell phone, set up a time and meet each other? Like modern people?
핸드폰 걸고 받고 약속하고 만날 생각은 없니 문명인 답게?
In the drama, the Goblin is called out when you blow out a candle.
드라마 속에서 도깨비는 촛불이 훅 꺼지면 인간앞에 소환이 되지만
But the Goblins in the fairy tales and legends historically don't appear in front of the people when you blow out the candle.
설화나 구전을 통해 본 역사 속 도깨비는 불을 분다고 사람들 앞에 나타나고 이런 대상이 아닙니다.
Of course, the recalling of the Goblin by candlelight isn't completely improbable.
물론 김은숙 작가가 쓴 촛불 소환이 전혀 개연성이 없는건 아니에요.
If you look at the literary reference Seokbosangjeol from Joseon dynasty during the King Sejong years, people wished to Goblins good fortune and long life.
조선 세종시대 문헌인 '석보상절'을 보면 사람들은 도깨비에게 복과 명을 빌었다고 나오는데요
As for candlelight recall, it may have come from the idea of ancestral worship ceremony or something like that...
촛불 소환은 이런 제사 혹은 제의에서 착안한 설정이 아닐까
I carefully suggest that idea.
조심스럽게 생각을 해봅니다.
Don't call me out anymore. You don't need to do that anymore. I'll be by your side from now on.
이제 소환하지마. 그럴 필요 없어 계속 옆에 있을 테니까.
[Goblin's healing place, buckwheat field]
도깨비의 힐링 장소 메밀밭
[Goblin likes buckwheat?]
도깨비는 메밀을 좋아한다?
It wasn't simply that he liked buckwheat. In our modern terms, I think he was a buckwheat maniac.
메밀을 좋아하는 정도가 아니라, 요즘 말로는 '덕후'였던 것 같습니다.
When I look at my research, it's not that he liked the buckwheat flower in the drama in a romantic sense...
자료를 보면 드라마 속 내용처럼 메밀꽃을 이렇게 로맨틱하게 좋아하는게 아니라
but he liked buckwheat very much as food.
음식으로써 메밀을 굉장히 좋아해요.
When I take a look at the records in Jeungsando...
'증산도 도전'같은 기록들을 보면요
there are stories where people try to reel Goblins in by making food with buckwheat that Goblins like.
사람들이 도깨비가 좋아하는 메밀로 스스로 이렇게 찾아오게끔 막 유도하는 그런 이야기들이 나오거든요?
According to the legend in the Jeolla province, Goblins don't have intestines. Because of that...
전라도 구절에 따르면 도깨비는 내장이 없대요.
they like buckwheat jello that is easy to digest. There are tales like that.
소화가 잘되는 메밀묵을 그렇게 좋아한다고, 그런 이야기도 있습니다.
You won't die even though you don't have a stomach.
너는 위가 없어도 안 죽어.
The second person of interest. Recalling Grim Reaper.
두 번째 의문 대상자 소환. 저승사자.
Born in the year Ge Choong, month Jeong Sa, day Eur Sa, fourth hour.
계충년 정사월 을사일 신사시 출생.
When a human dies, he brings them in to the world beyond. [The Grim Reaper manages the dead]
인간이 죽으면 저승으로 데리고 가는 대리자죠.
It's you, right?
본인 맞으시죠?
When I die later, perhaps I should become a Grim Reaper like the Uncle down the hall.
나도 나중에 죽으면 끝방삼촌처럼 저승사자나 할까봐.
I don't want to say this, but you have to commit a grave sin in your past life to become a Grim Reaper...
이런 말 하기 싫지만 전생에 큰 죄를 지어야 저승사자..
In the drama, it's said that someone with grave sin in the past life can become a Grim Reaper.
드라마에서는 전생에 죄가 있는 사람이 저승사자가 된다는 설정이 있어요.
How did you find out?
너 어떻게 안 것이냐?
There's no tale that says a sinner became a Grim Reaper. [False]
죄인이 저승사자가 됐다는 설화는 없습니다.
Among Korean Narrative Literature...
'한국구비문학대계'중에서
there is a story of Master Kim who used to be a government official who becomes a Grim Reaper after his death.
벼슬을 하던 김대감이 죽은 다음에 저승사자가 된 이야기가 나오긴 나와요.
But not because he was a criminal, but because he was a government official while he was alive...
죄인이라고 해서 된게 아니라, 이승에서 나라일을 하던 벼슬아치가 죽어서
that's how he came to work as an official of the dead.
저승의 일을 하게 된 셈이래요.
Narrative tales develop over a long period of time and...
설화라는 것은 오랜 기간 동안 무수하게 발전하고
disappear, and transform. They go through these processes.
사라지고 변형되고 발전하는 이런 과정을 거칩니다. 그래서
What I told you are some of the reasonable conclusions you can draw from these narrative tales.
제가 드린 말씀들은 그런 설화 속에서 그나마 가장 합리적인 어떤 결론들을 말씀드리게 되는거구요.
The new process of developing stories of Goblins...
도깨비에 대한 이야기는 오늘 우리가 새롭게 만들어가는 그 자체로 우리가
I believe we enjoyed the time we spent doing that.
행복한 시간을 보내는 것이 아닐까, 이런 생각을 해봅니다.
I'll move on to the next letter. ID is Ting-Kke-Bell.
계속해서 다음 사연 또 읽어드릴게요. 아이디 '팅깨벨'님께서 보내주신 사연인데요.
Yook (Yook Sung Jae), Jal (Handsome), Tdoe (Again), heart, heart, heart. Our Deuk Hwa, our god, you were the best!
육잘또 하트,하트,하트. 우리 덕화! 우리 신님 최고 였어요.
He said, "Please release all the behind-the-scenes of Yook Jal Tdoe."
우리 육잘또 비하인드 있는 대로 풀어 놔주세요. 라고 하셨어요.
Wow, our lovable Deok Hwa.
-네. -네, 정말 사랑스러운 덕화씨.
He was always so cute.
언제나 귀여움을 참 독차지 했었죠.
He's so hard-working and kind. He was really busy, you know.
아주 성실하고 착하고 사실 진짜 바빴잖아요
- That's right. - He had so many different things to do in his schedule.
-성재씨는 다른 스케쥴들이 많이 있어서. -맞아요, 네.
As for behind-the-scenes from the filming location, we have lots of scenes for you on the Goblin Special Part 2 tomorrow. Please anticipate.
촬영장 비하인드는 내일 공개될 소환 2부에 잔뜩 쌓여있으니까 기대 해주시구요.
Today, Yook Sung Jae has sent us self-camera takes from the filming location himself.
오늘은 더욱더 특별히 우리 육성재 군께서 직접 촬영장에서 셀프 카메라를 찍어서 보내주셨다고 합니다.
- I'm so excited. - I'm also very curious to see it as well.
-아, 너무 기대돼요! -저도 어떻게 나왔을지 참 궁금합니다.
- Yes. - Let's take a look together.
-네. -함께보시죠.
[Deok Hwa's self-camera footage]
덕화의 셀프카메라
Hello, Goblin viewers.
안녕하세요 도깨비 시청자 여러분들.
I will try to capture lovely and cool moments at the shooting sight as much as possible. [Deok Hwa will reveal the shooting sight in person!]
도깨비의 촬영 현장을, 이쁘고 멋있는 모습 많이 담아보도록 하겠습니다.
It is... 2:30 am right now.
지금은 새벽 2시 반입니다.
It is 2:30, the day which episodes 15 and 16 are going to be aired. [1/21/2017 AM The last day of filming and airing]
15,16화 마지막 화를 앞둔 그 날 당일의 두시 반입니다.
2:30 am.
오전 두시 반.
[The first guests on Deok Hwa Cam?]
덕화캠의 첫번째 게스트는?
Hello.
안녕하세요.
We are getting along well.
사이 좋아요.
They were talking about... what they are going to sing.
저 두 분이서 저 때 뭘 얘기 했었냐면은, 부를 노래 얘기하고 있었어요.
Shin Tak couple.
신탁커플.
♬ Among these many people [The song Goblin and Eun Tak sang at the post-wedding party]
이렇게 많은 사람들 가운데~
♬ I am happy to meet you [They chose by Trip Sketch]
그대 만난 건 나 역시 기쁨이야~
[The second guest on Deok Hwa Cam] This is... Grim Reaper Hyung.
이 쪽은 저승이 형입니다.
Dong Wook Hyung.
동욱이 형.
[Soulless] Yes, Deok Hwa.
왜 또 왔어.
How do you feel about our last day of shooting?
마지막 촬영 소감이 어떠신가요?
[Grabbing his hand]
덥석
I see...
그랬구나.
Deok Hwa thought of me as...
덕화가 나를
It's nice. Nice getting to put an end with many people.
좋네요. 이렇게 마지막에 북적북적하게 끝낼 수 있어서 좋고
It's quite amusing to get to meet Secretary Kim in person whom I only got to see
항상 TV로만 뵙던 김 비서님을 직접 뵈니까
on TV.
신기하네요.
[Rehearsing the last scene]
7도로, 7도로 맞췄어.
He's here.
오셨습니다.
- Hello.
-안녕하세요.
Oh, hello.
어, 안녕하세요.
[Grim Reaper and Secretary Kim finally meet for the first time]
은탁아!
I only saw you on TV.
맨날 TV로만 뵙다가.
[Awkward, nervously sticking out. Revealing heart of a fan]
그러게요.
I get to see you on the very last day.
마지막에 처음 뵙네요.
This is my first time meeting the Grim Reaper.
저승사자는 처음 만나요.
This was our first meeting since we had no scenes together.
사실 같이 찍는 씬이 없어서 이때 처음으로 뵌 거 였거든요.
I told him at the wrap party that I am his fan.
제가 쫑파티때도 말씀드렸어요.
I guess you didn't prepare certain things.
딱히 뭐 준비하신건 없나봐요?
You seem like you're just shooting everything.
그냥 무작정 찍으시는거 같은데.
Yes, just...
네, 그냥...
[Wannabe rapper dissing endlessly] I should ask this or stuff like that... Guess you haven't prepared anything.
뭘 질문해야겠다, 뭘 이렇게 준비도 안하시고..
There is your best scene, in my opinion.
아, 제가 제가 생각하는 형의 베스트 명장면이 있어요.
Please explain.
설명해주세요.
- At the tea shop. - Okay.
찻집에서 이제
Mom and son... Mom and a kid came...
엄마와 아들이 애기가..
Umm~ [Ah~ that scene.]
와서
"This is heaven you ordered."
-주문하신 천국 나왔습니다. -맞아요, 맞아요.
Ah, I really loved that one.
우와, 저 그거 진짜 너무 좋아, 너무 좋아요 진짜.
It was really sad shooting that scene.
그 씬을 찍으면서 되게 찡했어요.
Let's watch it now. [Let's watch the highlight that even made the  Grim Reaper sad!]
보시죠.
Mommy ordered heaven. [This touching scene shows the consideration of Mom and the Grim Reaper towards]
엄마는 천국을 주문했어.
[the child who faced sudden death]
엄마와 저승사자의 배려가 감동적이었던 장면
This is heaven you ordered.
주문하신 천국 나왔습니다.
It was really cool.
진짜 멋있었어요.
For me,
저는 덕화랑
I remember the first day of shooting together with Deok Hwa. Our first shoot in front of the house.
처음 촬영할 때가 기억나요. 우리 집앞에서 처음 찍을 때.
- I was really nervous back then. - Right.
- 아, 그 때 진짜 긴장 많이 됐는데. - 맞아요.
That was... about 4 months ago, right?
그게 벌써 한 4개월 전이죠?
Time flies.
진짜 빨리가네요.
Time really does fly.
시간이 잘 지나가네요.
When is BTOB's come-back?
컴백은 언제해요?
Every moment with you, Hyung, was great for me.
형과 함께하는 모든 순간들이 너무 좋았어요.
Oh, I see.
그랬구나...
[The last guest on Deok Hwa Cam, Soulmate CEO Kim] This is CEO Kim.
김 대표님 입니다.
Hello, everyone.
여러분 안녕하세요.
[Happy New Lunar Year.]
새해 복 많이 받으세요.
You haven't forgotten about your promise, right?
공약 거신 거 아직 안 까먹으셨죠?
When we reach the tvN's highest viewer ratings...
tvn 최고 시청률...
You said you would dance to Twice's TT.
갱신시에 트와이스의 TT를 추신다고.
I'm not sure why I said that. [CEO Kim who received oblivion as God's consideration?]
왜 그랬는지 모르겠습니다.
I'm looking forward to it.
- 기대가 많이 되네요. - 공약은
Yes, the promise should be kept, right?
공약은 지켜드려야 되겠죠?
I'm practicing here and there.
네, 틈틈이 연습하고 있습니다.
♬  It's a beautiful life  ♬
♫ It`s a beautiful life  ♫
[Goblin broke Reply 1988's record, 20% viewers ratings] [Goblin set a new record for a cable drama... Final episode 20.5%] [The last episode of Goblin recorded the highest rating for a tvN drama... over 20%]
♫ 난 너의 곁에 있을게 ♫
- Oh, pledge! -  Do we finally get to see it? TT? [Oh my, can't wait]
-공약! -드디어 볼 수 있는건가요 TT?
[High expectations] Oh, oh.
오, 오, 오!
♬ I'm like TT... [If you are curious about Secretary Kim's TT, keep watching]
I'm like TT~
- Oh, pledge! - Do we finally get to see it? TT? [Oh my, can't wait]
- 공약! - 드디어 볼 수 있는건가요 TT?
[High expectations] Oh, oh. [Let's see how Secretary Kim's keeping his promise!]
오,오,오!
[Cute] ♬ I'm like TT.
♪ I'm like TT~
[Perfect expression] ♬ Just like TT.
♪ just like TT~
♬ You don't know how I feel, so mean, so mean.
♪ 이런 내맘 모르고 너무해 너무해~
[Perfectly synced] ♬  I'm like TT.
♪ TT~
♬ Just like TT.
♪ just like TT~
♬ You don't know how I feel, so mean, so mean. [Secretary Kim knows  how I feel, good job.]
♪ 이런 내 맘 모르고 너무해! 너무해!
So, this was from Secretary Kim who has an extreme job.
지금까지 극한 직업의 김 비서였습니다.
Is it all set?
됐나요?
Yes, it's set.
네, 됐습니다.
[Sunny is still mesmerized]
아직도 감탄 중인 써니
Ah, he's so cute.
아이, 너무 귀여우시다.
He's cool. He said, "Is it all set?" very politely at the end.
멋있어요. 오 마지막에 또 정중하게 '됐나요?'.
He's good at dancing to girl groups' songs.
걸그룹 댄스를 잘하세요 가만 보면.
Yes, he's good.
네, 잘하세요.
- Dong Wook. - Yes?
- 동욱씨! - 네?
You should dance a little bit, too.
동욱 씨도 조금 보여주세요.
That? TT? [Everyone, get ready to capture screenshots]
방금 저거요 TT?
♬ TT. TT.
♪ TT~TT~
♬ You don't know how I feel, so mean, so mean. [As a gift for breaking the highest 20% viewer ratings]
♪ 내 맘 모르고 너무해! 너무해!
Since we broke the 20% viewer ratings, I made a little contribution as well.
20프로 넘었으니까, 저도 오늘 한 번 같이 슬쩍 숟가락 얹어 봤습니다.
Ah, Secretary Kim and Dong Wook, you both are so cute.
네, 정말 김비서님도 동욱씨도 너무 귀엽네요.
[Thanks to Secretary Kim and Grim Reaper for leaving great screenshots.]
♫ 이런 내 맘 모르고 너무해 너무해 ♫
We prepared small, but important awards for various brilliant moments for our Goblin Special. [ Inside awards prepared by Goblin Recall Special ]
도깨비의 스페셜에서 빛났던 열연의 순간들을 모아서 작지만 큰 어워즈를 준비해 보았습니다.
There are awards for tv shows at the end of the year but
원래 또 이 모든 드라마는 연말에 또 시상식이 있는데
we are throwing one just for us since it's not the end of year yet.
저흰 또 자체적으로 연말이 아니니까 준비해봤습니다.
Yes, it's called "Goblin Nation! God (sounds similar to "scene") ordainment." Let's watch together!
네, 이름바 '도깨비 나라! 신 임명식' 지금부터 바로 만나보시죠.
Okay!
네!
There is God in every little thing,
아주 작은 것에도
so I am always listening.
신이 깃들어 있으므로 늘 듣고 있었다.
Goblin story that lasted for 51 days...
50일 동안 그대들 곁에 머물렀던 도깨비 이야기.
Every single scene will be remembered.
그 어떤 장면도 잊히지 않으리라.
Today, for the last time, I am going to show you
오늘은 마지막으로 내가 선택한
the best scenes and the best lines that I picked.
명장면 명대사를 공개한다.
This, too,
이 역시
is the last reward that I give you in this lifetime.
내가 이승에서 내리는 마지막 상이다.
[God (Scene) Ordainment]
신 임명식
[Cute scene. The cutest character]
귀여우신
[Candidate 1. Full of lovely expressions. Grim Reaper.] It's going, it's going.
신호 간다, 신호 간다.
Hey! Don't!
야, 하지마!
If you won't call then why get her number?
안 걸거면 왜 받아 와?
[Feeling distressed, cute expressions] To appear human. You never know when I would call.
인간처럼 보이려고 언젠간 전화 할 지도 모르니까!
What do you like, Woo Bin?
우빈씬 뭐 좋아하세요?
[More cute expressions from someone in love] Sunny.
써니 씨요.
- Hobbies, something like that. - Sunny.
-취미 뭐 그런거요. -써니 씨요.
Am I... not cute?
저 안 귀엽나요?
Seriously, am I not cute?
근데 진짜 안 귀엽나요?
[Candidate 2. 900-year old Aegyo master. Goblin.]
귀여우신 후보 2
I want to leave! Leave!
나, 나갈래! 나갈래!
Ah, what are you going to do?
아, 어떡하실 거냐구요!
I will stop taking the pills so... [Full of aegyo even right after waking up]
내 약을 끊을터이니
Why are you suddenly lowering your voice?
목소리는 갑자기 왜 까시는지?
You won't know even if I tell you.
알다가도 모르겠구나.
I can buy you everything from here to there.
내가 여기서부터 저기까지 다 사줄 수도 있어.
In a single payment. [More cute when drunk]
일시불.
From here to here.
여기서부터 여기까지.
Ta da.
따다~
[Candidate 3. Extremely charming eye-smile. Ji Eun Tak.] -  What's your type? - W-What do you mean?
어떤 타입이에요?
Your ideal bride. A good wife and wise mother? Sexy? [Sweet eye-smile]
아내 타입! 현모양처? 섹시?
Should I change it up everyday?
아, 매일 매일 바꿔줄까요?
You said I was no good, that I was really no good!
너 나 별로 라며, 되게 별로 라며!
I said all sorts of things. Cancel.
제가 별 소릴 다했네요. 취소!
I don't feel like eating beef today. Let's eat something else. [Eye-smile that melts your heart]
오늘은 소느낌 아니에요 딴 거 먹어요.
Mister, 12 o'clock strikes! January 1st, the New Year! I just became an adult!
아저씨 열두시 땡! 1월 1일 새해! 저 방금 어른 됐어요!
[Guess the cutest character?]
과연 이 구역의 최강 귀요미는?
[Cute scene. Grim Reaper!]
귀여우신 저승사자!
It's me!
- 와! - 와, 나다!
Congratulations! [The Grim Reaper is truly happy.]
축하드립니다!
Thank you very much. Even though I didn't try to be cute, thanks for seeing me like that.
아, 예. 너무너무 감사드리고 제가 그렇게 일부러 한 건 아니지만 귀엽게 봐주셔서 감사합니다.
Am I not cute?
제가 안 귀엽나요?
Why are you staring me like that, making me uncomfortable?
뭘 그렇게 뚤어져라 봐 부담스럽게.
Should I watch you on TV then?
그럼 난 테레비로 봐?
Can't I look at you since we are shooting together? I'm on this show, too. [Whiny, whiny]
아, 뭐 같이 찍는데 좀 보면 안돼? 나도 이 드라마 나오는데?
Alright, I will see you on TV from now on. [Shooting site full of laughter because of the cute Grim Reaper]
알았어 그럼 테레비로 볼게.
[Mean scene. The character who acted mean very well.]
얄미우신
[Candidate 1. The top of meanness. Eun Tak's aunt.] You say you don't have the bank book?
네가 이러고도 통장이 없어? 어?
Give it back, please. I was just going to keep it as a souvenir. [Trying to take Eun Tak's mom's insurance money]
주세요 그냥 기념으로 갖고 있으려고 했던 거에요.
Why is this a souvenir? When in the world have you been here for this to be a souvenir?
이게 왜 기념이야? 뭐가 기념이야? 네가 이런데 언제 가봤다고 기념이야?
Oh, good. I'm glad I got you today. This is how you repay me for raising you?
어, 그래 너 오늘 잘걸렸어 네가 키워준 은혜를 이따구로 갚어?
Like this? Like this? Like this?
이따구로? 이따구로? 이따구로?
Where are you looking at with those eyes? [Eun Tak's aunt bothers Eun Tak even after she died]
눈을 똑바로 뜨고
Hey, I can't go like this since it's not fair. If I had that bank book...
야, 나 이대로는 못가지 억울해서. 그 통장만 있었어도.
[Candidate 2. Craziness that gives chills. Park Joong Hun.] What are you doing? Make him kneel!
뭐하느냐, 죄인을 꿇려라!
The criminal's gaze is causing the royal mind to be in disarray. [Manipulating Wang Yeo from behind]
죄인의 눈빛이 흉흉하니 어심이 어지럽다.
Make sure to kill him!
반드시 참하라!
Everyone says I did no wrong. Only you say I did. [The one that killed loyal Kim Shin Queen Kim Seon]
모두 소신의 처사라 옳다하는데 황후만이 틀렸다 하십니다.
Must you really...
그대가 정녕.
Is it me that covered his eyes, or is it the king that closed his eyes?
소신이 눈을 가린 것인지 폐하가 눈을 감은 것인지...
- You insolent...! - You wench!
-네 이놈! -네 이년!
[Candidate 3. Homeroom teacher that no one wants to have. She only says mean things to Eun Tak.] What time do you think it is?
몇 시야 지금?
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
You are a senior. How can a senior come to school in the 3rd period?
너 고 3이야, 고3이 어떻게 3교시에 등교를 해?
Do you come to school to eat lunch?
너 급식먹으러 학교에 오니?
Ji Eun Tak, I'm most afraid when someone like you is good at studying.
지은탁 난 너같은 애가 공부 잘하는게 참 무서워.
Doing all the wrong things behind my back. It is kids like you that cause troubles once in society.
뒤로는 호박씨나 까고, 너 같은 애들이 사회 나가서 분란 일으키는 거야.
[Guess the meanest scene-stealer that even breathes meanly?]
과연, 숨 쉬는 것마저 얄미운 신스틸러는?
[Mean scene. Eun Tak's aunt!]
얄미우신 은탁 이모!
I just did what was written on the script.
이 자릴 빌어서, 저는 작가님이 써주신 대로 한 거거든요.
Thanks to the writer for making me very mean. You don't even have a trophy?
얄밉게 써주신 작가님한테 감사드리고. 상패도 없나요?
Where is the reward money?
상금 어딨냐고?
I said where is the reward money?
상금 어딨냐고!
[You know I'm joking, right?]
장난인 거 아시죠?
Thank you. thank you. [Eun Tak's aunt is so happy to have the reward]
아, 고맙습니다! 고맙습니다.
I will keep it from my nephew. I will keep it well. Thank you.
제가 조카한테 안 뺏기고 잘 간직할게요. 고맙습니다.
[Tough scene. Who is the toughest character?]
터프하신
[Candidate 1. The Grim Reaper, throwing garbage in a single shot. Very cold-hearted cool guy.]
터프하신 후보 1
I'm rooting for the path that's ahead of you.
응원한다 너의 합격.
And the things that you will do in the future. Let's go inside.
앞으로 네가 할 일들, 들어가자.
[Candidate 2. King of rage, Goblin.] I love you, too... Mister.
나도 사랑? 아저씨!
- Shut up! - Love you...
-닥쳐! -사랑.
You insolent! ["You insolent!" full of rage.]
네 이놈!
Hyung, what did you do last night?
-형 어제 누구랑 뭐했는데? - 네 이놈!
- You insolent! - You don't even remember!
생각 안나네 안나!
[Candidate 3. Unique girl-crush Sunny] Why isn't this person answering his call? What on earth is this man?
이 인간은 대체 왜 전화를 안 받는거야? 뭐하는 인간이야 대체?
I am...
저는...
This jerk... Should I just kill him?
이 새끼 진짜 죽여 버릴까?
At the cafe where we last met. 1 pm tomorrow. Don't care if he comes as a manager or a general manager. Make sure to come. If he is late,
전에 봤던 카페, 내일 오후 한시, 과장으로 오든 부장으로 오든 오라고 늦으면
I will kill him. Please deliver this message.
죽여버린다고 전해주세요.
[Guess the toughest character?]
과연 터프함의 최강자는?
[Tough scene. Sunny.]
우와!!!
[Congratulations!] Wow!
우와!!
Say something, say.
수상 소감, 수상 소감!
Thank you, Director and Writer. Thanks to my parents as well.
감독님, 작가님 감사하구요. 부모님 감사합니다.
And "This jerk... should I kill him?"
-아, 그리고 '이 새끼 죽여버릴까?' -네.
For acting so well so I can say the line, "This jerk... Should I kill him?", naturally,
-'이 새끼 죽여버릴까?'라는 대사를 이렇게 -네,네.
I would like to thank Lee Dong Wook [The Grim Reaper is a little bit scared of Sunny]
저절로 나올 수 있도록 연기를 잘해주신 이동욱씨께
and share this honor.
영광을 돌리겠습니다.
So you wanted to kill me?
죽이고 싶었군요? 감사합니다.
[Thank you again.]
네.
[Humorous scene. Find the king of ad-libs!]
센스가 남다르신
[Candidate 1. Master of ad-libs, The Grim Reaper. This is a scene that he's debating which voice he will use to answer Sunny's call.]
샌스가 남다르신 후보 1
Hello, this is...
안녕하세요. 저는.
Should I... go a little bit tougher than that? What are you up to?
좀 거칠게 나가볼까? 뭐해?
You don't recognize my voice? It's a voice you can't forget that easily. [The script only asked him to use a different tone of voice.]
내 목소리 몰라? 잊을 만한 목소리가 아닌데!
This is not it.
이것도 아니야.
Hello. Oh my, hello.
여보세요, 오홍~여보세요.
[This became one of the best scenes because of this master of ad-libs.] Hello?
여보세요?
[Candidate 2. Textbook of ad-libs, Goblin] [The script was only up to "shut up"]
센스가 남다르신 후보 2
I love you, too... Mister.
나도 사랑? 아저씨.
Shut up!
-닥쳐! -사랑?
- Love you... - You insolent! [With an extra line, this scene got even better.]
네 이놈!
[Candidate 3. Yoo Deok Hwa, who came to love ad-libs. The script ended with the Goblin patting Deok Hwa's head.] Are you really giving this to me, Uncle?
이, 이거 진짜 나 주는거야 삼촌?
This is a reward from me.
내가 주는 상이다.
I haven't done anything to deserve a reward though.
나 상 받을 짓 한거 없는데?
You have worked hard to grow up well.
잘 크느라 고생했다.
I love you. [An ad-lib, "I love you," that melted the Goblin's heart.]
사랑해요.
This kid...
이 자식이.
[Guess the master of the best ad-libs?]
과연 역대급 애드리브의 달인은?
[The most humorous scene, Grim Reaper!]
센스가 남다르신 저승사자!
[Two times medalist!]
우와!!
Double medals!
2관왕!!
Thank you. I got to be a two-time medalist including the most humorous scene.
감사합니다, 예. 애드리브 상까지 2관왕을 거머쥐게 되었습니다. 정말 너무 감사드리구요.
I will share this honor with Sunny.
이 영광을 써니 씨와 함께하도록 하겠습니다.
- That, that. Please ask me that. - Which one? - "What is your hobby?"
그거, 그거 빨리 해주세요. 취미가 뭐에요.
What is your hobby?
취미가 뭐에요?
Sunny.
써니 씨요.
Sunny!
써니씨요.
Thank you.
감사합니다!
[Ad-libs that weren't aired!]
방송엔 미처 공개되지 못한 애드리브!
White pants, white pants!
어, 흰 바지, 흰 바지!
I did it earlier.
아까 했잖아~
[Didn't know~]
몰랐지~
I'm so happy. Even though it's not real, I'm happy to be awarded. - Of course. [The radio booth brightened up]
-아, 기쁘네요 이게 뭐라고 또 상을 받으니까 굉장히 굉장히 기쁘네요. -아이, 그럼요 기쁘네요.
It feels like we split the rewards among ourselves but it still feels good to be awarded.
이거 은근히 저희끼리 다 나눠 먹는거 같긴 하지만 그래도 이렇게 하나씩 다 받으니까 좋네요.
Yes, I'm happy. By the way, Dong Wook, you should treat us to something since you got double medals.
네, 행복하네요. 아니 동욱씨 2관왕 하셨잖아요? 이따 한턱 쏘세요.
Because I got two medals? Alright. I will treat you to anything you want.
2관왕 했으니까, 알겠습니다. 뭐 드시고 싶은거 제가 사도록 하겠습니다.
[The Grim Reaper has a heart and a wallet as wide as the Pacific Ocean] Okay, okay.
네,네!
3,000 won ($3) per person.
1인당 3천원 선에서.
[He is a master of ad-libs, for sure.]
역시 애드리브 장인
Congratulations for getting the Toughest Scene.
터프하신 수상 진심으로 축하드리고
Congratulations for getting the Cutest Scene and the Most Humorous Scene.
동욱씨도 귀여우신, 또 센스가 남다르신까지 축하드립니다.
Alrighty.
네, 알겠습니다.
So from our first meeting to God (scene) ordainment, we got to watch
자, 이렇게해서 화제의 첫 만남부터 신 임명식까지 도깨비 소환 스페셜
the Goblin Summon Special part 1, Summon to the living.
1부 이승으로 소환 만나보셨는데요
How was it? This special episode?
어떠셨어요 오늘 이 스페셜 방송?
They were the scenes that weren't aired.
사실 그 방송에서 볼 수 없었던 장면들이 잖아요?
So it was really fun. It felt like looking back on our memories, rather than working.
그러니까 너무 재밌었고 지금 일하는 기분보다는 그냥 이렇게 저희 추억을 하나하나 되짚어 보는 느낌?
You are right.
맞아요.
I enjoyed it very much.
굉장히 즐겁네요.
When I heard we were airing special episodes, I wished that day would come soon and waited so much.
네, 스페셜 방송한다고 해서 저는 '어, 빨리 그 날이 왔으면 좋겠다, 너무 보고싶다' 생각을 했었는데
Since we could watch this before anyone else...
저희가 이렇게 먼저 볼 수 있어서.
That's right. It's an honor.
그쵸, 큰 영광이죠.
- Yes. - I'm so happy we could see it early.
-미리보게 돼서 너무너무 기쁩니다. -네.
But on the other hand, it's kind of sad, too. The show is really over.
반면에 아쉬운 마음도 좀 들어요. 이제 진짜 드라마가 다 끝나서
That's why we are reviewing the old memories.
우리가 또 이렇게 추억을 되짚고 있구나, 이런 생각도 들고.
I'm sure there are many people who feel just like me. [Viewers who feel sad and bittersweet!]
저 같은 분들, 시청자 분들 많으실거라 생각됩니다.
- Right. - But we are allowed a little more time to be with Goblin, right?
하지만 우리에겐 이 드라마 도깨비와 생을 함께할 시간이 조금더 허락이 되있죠?
Yes, that's right. At the same time tomorrow. For the first time in our nation. [Feb 4, 6:40 pm]
네, 그렇습니다. 저희는 바로 내일 이 시간 국내 최초
I mean, for the first time in this lifetime, we are going to show you more behind-the-scenes.
아니죠 이승최초로 드라마 도깨비의 비하인드 영상들이 다 공개되는
We will come back with Special episode 2.
도깨비 소환 스페셜 2부로 여러분을 찾아 뵐 예정이니까요
Please look forward to it.
기대 많이 많이 해주세요.
Alright. We will see you tomorrow then.
네, 그럼 내일 또 만나요.
Bye~!!
안녕!
Pray with all your heart. We will show you the behind-the-scenes that were never aired.
간절하게 빌어, 어디에도 공개 되지않은 비하인드도 보여줄거야.
♬ You're so beautiful. You're beautiful. I said you're beautiful ♬
♫ 너 정말 이쁘다 이쁘다 이쁘다니까 ♫
I can do it! Please give me a kiss.
♫  내 말 믿지 않는 건데  ♫ 이 쪽에다 뽀뽀해주세요.
- Thank you. - Fighting!
-고맙습니다 -파이팅!
- What are you doing? - What, why?
무슨 짓이야!
I'm being competitive.
승부욕이야.
Did Dong Wook do this?
동욱이가 그랬어?
Freeze.
얼음!
Right, right.
그쵸,그쵸.
Do I get up and go next to him?
일어나서 옆으로 가요?
- Cut, okay. - Didn't the camera just come into the the frame?
-컷, 오케이. -카메라 들어오지 않았어?
The viewers don't think it's a CG.
시청자들은 CG라고 생각을 못해.
Our drama is all about CG, you know.
우리 드라마는 CG드라마 인데.
Please catch the original airing! You know what I mean?
본방사수 꼭 해주세요. 제 말 무슨 뜻인줄 알죠?